Hello, my name is Sayantan.
This is a work in collaboration with
Carl Marshall, Derek Nowrouzezahrai,
Zhao Dong, and Zhengqin Li.
We present a novel graphics primitive that uses
a network of memory instead of
connected layers of perceptrons.
One of the primary advantage of
using our technique is that it
makes inferencing more efficient compared
to traditional multi-layer perceptrons.
This paper shows a variety of application of
our technique in the context of neural graphics
pipeline, such as Textures, Signed Distance
Fields, Shading and Neural Radiance Fields.
We note that our technique is very
general and may extend easily to
other applications in graphics and beyond.
At a high level, our technique
blurs the line between learning
and memorization. We hope to spur more
interesting discussions and ideas in
this context and in the context
of neural networks in general.
Next, we introduce our technique
differentiable indirection. It is
similar to pointer indirection,
where we query a memory location
that points to another memory location
containing the final output. However,
in our case, we learn the pointer
values using gradient descent.
Both pointers and the outputs
are stored on multi-dimensional
regular grids. Since the array cells are discrete,
we linearly interpolate the neighbouring cells
to enable continuous output and backpropagation.
A key feature of such array is that
they are fully differentiable. That is,
we compute the gradient not only w.r.t to the
content of the table but also with respect to the
array coordinates. The latter enables learning
of the pointers as stored in the first array.
We call the first array primary,
as shown in orange, and the second
array as cascaded, highlighted in blue.
We use a combine primary and cascaded in a variety
of configuration to enable various applications.
To better understand our technique,
we highlight one simple application
of differentiable indirection in the
context the context of PBR shading.
Specular BRDF lobes are often
modelled using isotropic-GGX,
as described by the following
equation. The equation has two
scalar inputs alpha and h; and outputs
a single-channel, non-linear HDR value.
Here, we use differentiable indirection to
approximate the function. The two inputs
to the function are used as the coordinates to
sample the primary array; a 2D with 2-channels.
The primary array then returns the 2D
coordinates to sample the cascaded array;
which contains the final output.
In this slide, we visualize
the learned representation of
Isotropic-GGX as stored in the
primary and cascaded arrays.
Here, we compare the analytic
and approximate output on a
scene rendered with a variety of
sharp and diffuse specular lobes.
The following plot shows the
key takeaways of our approach.
We compare the resource utilization
for various alternative neural
architectures for the same task.
Note that our technique requires
fewer compute flops and memory
bandwidth compared to MLPs and lesser parameter
space compared to single level lookup-table.
Next, we next show a variety of other
applications of differentiable indirection.
We start with our SDF representation.
Our technique uses a 3D primary
and a 3D cascaded array.
We query the primary with a
spatial coordinate and the representation
learns a mapping from spatial coordinates
to binary density, either a plus or a minus 1.
Here, positive, and negative indicates exterior
and interior of a geometry respectively.
The output of the representation is used
to construct a 3D mesh using
marching cubes algorithm.
The video compares a reference Kd-tree oracle
on left, with our technique and
multi-resolution hash-encoding.
Notice the piano keys and the space
between the two plates of the piano cover.
The next application uses differentiable
indirection for image compression.
Here we use uv-coordinates to query a 2D primary
with 4 channels while the cascaded is
4D array storing the output RGB values.
Our empirical observations show that
increasing the dimensionality of the
cascaded array improves the quality
of output at a given compression.
Here we show the output of our
technique at 6x compression.
Next, we make a small modification to the
compression-only network to also incorporate
texture sampling based on pixel footprint.
The network additionally uses a
pixel-footprint estimate to output an
alias-free, LOD appropriate RGB output.
We show its application in regular
albedo textures and normal maps.
Notice how seamlessly we transition
from coarse LOD to fine LOD using
our technique while compressing the
representation by 6x at the same time.
We also perform a uv stress test comparing our
technique with ASTC nearest neighbor sampling.
Our technique produces slightly blurrier (refer to uncompressed video link at the end) results at coarse LODs closer to the distant horizon.
ASTC produces much nosier results
at comparable sample count.
Next application shows the approximation
of Disney BRDF using our approach.
Similar to isotropic GGX, Disney BRDF models the
appearance of a variety of complex materials.
In this application we split primary
and cascaded into an offline-encoder
and a runtime-decoder to improve efficiency.
The offline encoder encodes artist-control
parameters, which are often stored as regular
textures into another set of encoded textures.
At runtime these encoded
textures are used by the decoder.
Again, we compare our technique
with the reference implementation.
Next, we show the an end-to-end combined texture
sampling and Disney shading
for two different scenes.
We move to our final application in
Radiance Field compression. Here,
we use two independent networks to compress
the density and the radiance field. Both
networks are queried by a 3D spatial
coordinate, One outputs a scalar density
and the other a 12 channel latent
vector. The latent vector is then
combined with view-directions using positional
encoding to output a view dependent RGB color.
The video shows the comparison between
reference uncompressed grid on the top-left
and multi-resolution hash encoding
compressed grid on the bottom-left.
Thus we conclude our video demonstration.
Thank you for watching.